Ben Sands Papers on Tufts Hockey MS245
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Ben Sands Papers on Tufts Hockey
circa 1930 -- 2015
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS245
2.15 Linear Feet
This collection contains materials created and compiled by Ben Sands (E1954), former player and later coach of the Tufts hockey team, including newsclippings and publications, photographs, programs and rosters, statistics, correspondence, admnistrative material, and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ben Sands, 2015-2018, accession number 2015.065.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series.
Biographical / Historical
Ben Sands, of North Reading, Massachusetts, graduated from Tufts University in 1954 and was a defenseman on the Tufts hockey team. Hockey was dropped as a varsity sport in 1960; in the early 1980s, Sands initiated and coached a club team, which regained varsity status in 1986. Sands coached the team for a total of six seasons, compiling a 73-63-4 record and earning ECAC Division III Coach of the Year in 1987-1988. His teams qualified for the ECAC playoffs in 1988, 1989, and 1991.
In the early 1990s, when financial constraints further threatened the team's status, Sands established the Friends of Tufts Hockey, a group which raised funds to support and sustain the hockey program. In 2001, Tufts joined the NESCAC hockey league. Sands also helped raise funds to turn old offices at the Malden rink where the Tufts team practices and plays into a locker room, which the team named the Ben Sands Locker Room in 2008.
In 2018, at the first Tufts Athletic Department Hall of Fame induction ceremony, Sands was honored with the inaugural Brown and Blue award for his work in bringing varsity ice hockey back to Tufts, and ensuring the team's survival.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials created and compiled by Ben Sands, former player on and coach of the Tufts hockey team. Materials include newsclippings and magazines about the Tufts hockey team and about hockey in the region; photographs; programs, schedules, rosters, and statistics; correspondence and letters from prospective players; admnistrative material; and Tufts memorabilia, including student handbooks, commencement materials, and sheet music.
Student life; Ice Hockey (Men's); Teamwork (Sports); Coaches (Athletics); Tufts University -- History; University history; Alumni collections
- Ben Sands papers on Tufts hockey, circa 1930 -- 2015; MS245.001; 2.15 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in rough chronological order and by accession. Original order was maintained where possible.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials created or kept by Ben Sands, former player on and coach of the Tufts hockey team. Materials include newsclippings and magazines about the Tufts hokcey team and about hockey in the region; photographs; programs, schedules, rosters, and statistics; correspondence and letters from prospective players; admnistrative material; and Tufts memorabilia, including student handbooks, commencement materials, sheet music, and a set of Tufts slippers and a beanie.
  - Student handbooks and tickets, 1934 -- 1938; MS245.001.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Open for research.
  - Photographs, 1940 -- 1990; MS245.001.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Winter sports schedules and programs, 1943 -- 2015; MS245.001.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boston Garden Sport News Magazine, 1949 -- 1950; MS245.001.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rosters, statistics, and hockey history, 1949 -- 2000; MS245.001.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1986 -- 2010; MS245.001.001.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings and hockey guide, 1955 -- 1957; MS245.001.001.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1956 -- 1991; MS245.001.001.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative material, 1976 -- 2010; MS245.001.001.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tufts Hockey Club information sheets, 1976 -- 1977; MS245.001.001.00010; 2 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Eastern College Hockey Magazine, 1988; MS245.001.001.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Prospective players, 1975 -- 1977; MS245.001.001.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Class of 1938 memorabilia, 1938 -- 1940; MS245.001.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oversize clippings, 1940 -- 1990; MS245.001.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Beta Mu invitation and program, 1937 -- 1938; MS245.001.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Donated by Ben Sands, 2018, accession MS-2019-038.
  - Tufts Placement Service "Employment Problems" pamphlet, 1938; MS245.001.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified photograph, circa 1937 -- 1938; MS245.001.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook and memorabilia, circa 1930 -- 1949; MS245.001.003; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box data_value_missing_231285e0dad02b29a68253e05099d125, Box 3)
    This file contains a scrapbook of clippings related to the Tufts hockey team, a Tufts beanie and set of slippers, and Tufts Jackson College class of 1938 photograph.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Scrapbook and photograph are extremely fragile and may require supervision while in use. Scrapbook has been photocopied and photocopies should be used for access when possible.